<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE plist PUBLIC "-//Apple//DTD PLIST 1.0//EN" "http://www.apple.com/DTDs/PropertyList-1.0.dtd">
<plist version="1.0">
<dict>
	<key>Root</key>
	<array>
		<dict>
			<key>Items</key>
			<array>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>Geneva was selected as the site for the CERN Laboratory in 1952. On 17 May 1954, the first shovel of earth was dug on the Meyrin site under the eyes of Geneva officials and members of CERN staff.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>DA.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1954: Excavating the CERN Site</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>One of the magnetic coils for the first CERN accelerator - the synchro-cyclotron (or the "SC") - being transported through Switzerland. The coil weighted 60 tonnes and was 7.2m in diameter. The SC operated for 34 years, starting in 1957.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>D2.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1957: SC - The First Machine</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>CERN's first computer, a huge vacuum-tube Ferranti Mercury, was a million times slower than today's big computers and took 3 months to install. It was replaced in 1960 by the transistor-powered IBM 709, seen here being unloaded in Geneva.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>D3.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1960: Computers for Physics</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>The Big European Bubble Chamber (BEBC) particle detector is seen here being installed. The stainless-steel vessel was filled with 35 cubic metres of liquid hydrogen. Charged particles left trails of bubbles as they passed through it.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>D4.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1971: BEBC - Bubble Chamber</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>The ISR (Intersecting Storage Rings). These accelerators, brought into service in 1971 and closed down in 1984, were the first of the proton-proton colliders. They were fed by the Proton Synchrotron (PS), which is still in operation at CERN.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>D5.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1971: First proton Collider</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>In July 1973 a groundbreaking discovery was announced at CERN: pictures (such as the one above) observed in the Gargamelle bubble chamber proved that the electromagnetic and weak forces were both facets of a single 'electroweak' force.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>D6.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1973: Neutral Current Discovery</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>On 31st July 1974 the machine used to excavate the 7km tunnel for the new Super Proton Synchrotron (SPS) returned to its starting point. The SPS was the first accelerator to span the French-Swiss border, 40m below the surface.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>D7.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1974: Construction of the SPS</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>Although the main accelerators at CERN are circular, the linear accelerators such as LINAC-1 shown here are used as a first step towards achieving the required particle energie. They use radio waves to accelerate charged particles.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>D8.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1975: Linear Accelerator</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>In 1983 the direct observation of two new particles, the W and Z, was announced. These particles had been predicted by theory and their discovery was the result of a huge effort from the accelerator (the SPS) and the detectors (UA1 and UA2).</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>D9.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1983: Discovery in the W and Z</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>Aerial view of the CERN region showing the path of the 27 kilometre tunnel that housed the largest scientific instrument ever made - the Large Electron-Positron collider (LEP). The same tunnel will be used for the Large Hadron Collider (LHC).</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>D10.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1989: LEP Collider</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>Soon after the LEP collider started operation, the four detectors (Aleph, Delphi, Opal and L3) announced proof that there are only 3 types of neutrino, as demonstrated by the agreement between the experimental data (solid points) and the theoretical predictions for 2, 3 or 4 neutrino types (curves).</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>DJ.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1990: Three Types of Neutrino</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>In 1996 the first anti-atoms (anti-protons paired with anti-electrons) were made, using the PS210 detector at the Low Energy Antiproton Ring (LEAR) pictured above. Anti-hydrogen is now routinely made at the CERN Antiproton Decelerator.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>DQ.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>1996: Antimatter in the Laboratory</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>In the fractions of a second after the Big Bang, quarks and gluons (the consituents of protons and neutrons) were free to move around in a 'primordial soup'. This state of matter, known as the 'quark-gluon plasma' was recreated at CERN in 2000.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>DK.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>2000: A New State of Matter</string>
				</dict>
			</array>
			<key>Title</key>
			<string>History</string>
		</dict>
		<dict>
			<key>Items</key>
			<array>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>t=0 seconds: temperature=infinite! Universe expands from a single point. t~10^-43 seconds: temperature=10^32K. Gravity "freezes out". Other 3 forces are indistinguishable.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>C2.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>The Big Bang</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>t~10^-35 seconds: temperature=10^27K. Inflation period; exponential expansion of the universe for a short period. t~10^-32 seconds: strong nuclear force "freezes out".</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>C3.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Grand Unification</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>t~10^-10 seconds: temperature=10^15K. Weak nuclear force "freezes out". All 4 forces are now distinct. Antiquarks and quarks annihilate, leaving an excess of matter. W and Z bosons decay.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>C4.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Electroweak Era</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>t~10-4 seconds: temperature=10^13K. Quarks combine to form protons and neutrons. Positrons and electrons annihilate and are not recreated. An excess of electrons remains.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>C5.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Protons and Neutrons form</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>t=3 minutes: temperature=10^9K. Temperature is low enough to allow protons and neutrons to combine to form nuclei (deuterium, helium, lithium). Conditions similar to interior of stars.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>C6.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Formation of Nuclei</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>t=300000 years: temperature=6000K. Electrons begin to orbit nuclei - atoms of hydrogen, helium and lithium are created, which light cannot break apart; universe becomes transparent.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>C7.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Era of Light and Atoms</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>t=1 billion years: temperature=18K. Stars and galaxies form. Synthesis of heavy nuclei (e.g. carbon, iron) starts occurring in stars. Even heavier nuclei form and disperse in supernovae.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>C8.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Galaxies Form</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>Quarks always combine to form "hadrons" with integer electric charge, e.g. protons and neutrons. Leptons differ from quarks in that they can be found in isolation and don't feel the effects of the strong nuclear force.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>C10.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Particles</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>Four forces are responsible for all of the interactions between particles. Each force has an associated "carrier" (in red) that transmits the force between one particle and another. Relative strenghts of the forces are also noted.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>CJ.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Forces</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string></string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>CQ.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Unification of Forces</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Description</key>
					<string>t=14 billion years: temperature=3K. Chemical processes have linked atoms to form molecules. From the dust of stars and through coded messages (DNA) humans emerge.</string>
					<key>Image</key>
					<string>C9.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Today</string>
				</dict>
			</array>
			<key>Title</key>
			<string>Physics</string>
		</dict>
		<dict>
			<key>Items</key>
			<array>
				<dict>
					<key>Items</key>
					<array>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>Although the main accelerators at CERN are circular, linear accelerators such as LINAC-1 shown here are used as a first step towards achieving the required particle energies. They use radio waves to accelerate charged particles.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>D8.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Linear Accelerator</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The LHC will accelerate protons (and heavy ions) to unprecedented energies, in order to answer some of the open questions in particle physics. Five de- tectors (ALICE, CMS+TOTEM, ATLAS, LHCb) will be placed around the 27km ring, about 100m underground.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>HJ.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Diagram of LHC with Detectors</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>1232 15m-long dipole magnets will be used to steer protons on their course around the LHC. The superconducting niobium-titanium/copper cables will be cooled by liquid helium to about -271°C – colder than outer space!</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>HK.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Production of LHC Dipoles</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>High temperature superconducting ma- terial (left of photo) is used to transmit 13000 amps to the low temperature superconductor of the LHC dipoles and quadrupoles. These "current leads" are immersed in liquid helium.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>HQ.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>LHC Current Leads</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>Particles travelling around the 27km LHC ring will be focused by 392 superconducting quadrupole magnets. They squeeze the billions of protons into bunches just a few microns wide.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>SJ.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>A Quadrupole Magnet for LHC</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>Controlling the world's largest scientific instrument is a complex task. 27km of magnets, accelerating cavities and crogenic installations will need to be monitored 24 hours a day, 7 days a week!</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>SK.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>The LHC Control Centre</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>These devices produce radio-frequency waves that the protons "ride", like a surfer riding a wave on the sea. After traversing these cavities many times, the protons approach the speed of light.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>SQ.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Accelerating Cavity for LHC</string>
						</dict>
					</array>
					<key>Thumbnail image</key>
					<string>LHC_about.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>LHC</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Items</key>
					<array>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>One of the magnetic coils for the first CERN accelerator - the synchro-cyclotron (or "SC") - being transported through Switzerland. The coil weighed 60 tonnes and was 7.2m in diameter. The SC operated for 34 years, starting in 1957.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>D2.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>1952: SC - The First Machine</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The ISR (Intersecting Storage Rings). These accelerators, brought into service in 1971 and closed down in 1984, were the first of the proton-proton colliders. They were fed by the Proton Synchrotron (PS), which is still in operation at CERN.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>D5.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>1971: First Proton Collider</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>Aerial view of the CERN region showing the path of the 27 kilometre tunnel that housed the largest scientific instrument ever made - the Large Electron-Positron collider (LEP). The same tunnel will be used for the Large Hadron Collider (LHC).</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>D10.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>1989: LEP Collider</string>
						</dict>
					</array>
					<key>Thumbnail image</key>
					<string>PREV_about.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>Previous Accelerators</string>
				</dict>
			</array>
			<key>Title</key>
			<string>Accelerators</string>
		</dict>
		<dict>
			<key>Items</key>
			<array>
				<dict>
					<key>Items</key>
					<array>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The ATLAS detector will search for new discoveries in the head-on collisions of protons accelerated in the LHC. ATLAS will be about 42m long, 22m in diameter and will weigh 7000 tonnes, making it the largest colliding-beam detector ever constructed.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>SA.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>The ATLAS Detector for LHC</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The ATLAS cavern in early 2004
In the centre, the support "feet" have been assembled. On the floor to the right are some modules of the tile calorimeter.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>S2.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>The ATLAS Cavern</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>One of the two endcap toroid magnet vacuum vessels. These 11m diameter devices will supply a magnetic field of 4.7 Tesla - more than 100000 times stronger than that of the earth.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>S3.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Endcap Toroid for ATLAS</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>An assembly of drift tubes for the ATLAS muon system. With careful timing of the pulses from these devices, muon positions can be measured to an accuracy of 0.1 mm.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>S4.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Drift Tubes for ATLAS</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The circular inner bore of the liquid-argon electromagnetic endcap calorimeter, and the hadronic endcap calorimeter wheels: two devices used to measure particle energies.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>S5.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Calorimeters for ATLAS</string>
						</dict>
					</array>
					<key>Thumbnail image</key>
					<string>ATLAS_about.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>ATLAS</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Items</key>
					<array>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>A "general purpose" detector designed to be sensitive to any new physics created in proton collisions in the LHC. CMS is based around the world's largest superconducting solenoid. More than 2800 physicists from 38 countries collaborate on this project.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>S6.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>The CMS Detector for LHC</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The CMS hadron calorimeter (HCAL -the gold-coloured device) will be inserted into the red magnet yoke ring. The HCAL will measure the energies of particles such as protons and pions.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>S7.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>The CMS HCAL &amp; Central Yoke</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>About 80000 crystals of lead tungstate (PbWO4) will form the CMS ECAL (electromagnetic calorimeter), to measure the energies of electrons and photons with unprecidented precision.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>S8.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Crystals for the CMS ECAL</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>Thin wafers of silicon, divided into strips or pixels finer than a human hair, will be used to measure the tracks of charged particles through CMS and identify positions of particle decays.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>S9.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Silicon Tracking Sensors for CMS</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>High energy particles incident on these wedges of steel produce light in the embedded quartz fibres. The amount of light produced gives a measure of the initial particle energy.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>S10.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>A Calorimeter for CMS</string>
						</dict>
					</array>
					<key>Thumbnail image</key>
					<string>CMS_about.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>CMS</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Items</key>
					<array>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>In addition to proton collisions, the LHC will also collide beams of heavy ions, in order to study the quark-gluon plasma. ALICE is dedicated to the study of this phase of matter that existed naturally for just a fraction of a second after the Big Bang.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>HA.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>The ALICE Detector for LHC</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The worlds largest warm solenoid is a legacy of the L3 experiment and the LEP era. Its 0.5 Tesla field provides the bending power for the thousands of particles emitted in heavy ion collisions.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>H2.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>The ALICE Solenoid Magnet</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>A spectacular view of the interior of the ALICE Time Projection Chamber (TPC) - the worlds largest. It measures the trajectories of the thousands of particles emitted in heavy ion collisions with sub-millimetre precision.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>H3.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>The ALICE TPC</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The extremely high volumes of data coming from the detectors of the LHC (equivalent to the data throughput of the world's telecom networks!) nece- ssitate high bandwidth communication networks, based on optical fibres.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>H4.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Optical Fibres for ALICE</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The ALTRO chip is a custom integrated circuit designed to be one of the building blocks of the front-end electronics for the ALICE Time Projection Chamber.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>H5.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Electronics for ALICE</string>
						</dict>
					</array>
					<key>Thumbnail image</key>
					<string>ALICE_about.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>ALICE</string>
				</dict>
				<dict>
					<key>Items</key>
					<array>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The LHCb experiment is specialized at studying particles containing beauty and antibeauty quarks. The aim is to find and measure the source of a mechanism that generated a tiny excess of matter over antimatter in the very early stages of the universe.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>H6.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>The LHCb Detector for LHC</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The LHCb magnet allows the measurement of particle momenta. It consists of two coils, weighing 27 tonnes each, mounted inside a steel yoke weighing 1450 tonnes.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>H7.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>Coils for the LHCb Dipole</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>The LHCb Hadron Calorimeter meas- ures the energies of particles contain- ing quarks. It comprises 500 tonnes of iron interleaved with transparent plastic plates. 80km of fibres transport light generated in these plates to sensors.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>H8.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>LHCb Hadron Calorimeter</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>Antimatter is the "mirror image" of matter. However, the mirror image is not always perfect. In about one case out of a thousand, antimatter behaves a little differently. Understanding this behaviour may help us understand why there is no antimatter in our universe.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>H9.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>CP Violation with LHCb</string>
						</dict>
						<dict>
							<key>Description</key>
							<string>One of the hexagonal mirrors used for the LHCb Ring Imaging Cerenkov (RICH) detector. This device provides a measure of particle speed, facilitating particle identification.</string>
							<key>Image</key>
							<string>H10.png</string>
							<key>Title</key>
							<string>The LHCb RICH Detector</string>
						</dict>
					</array>
					<key>Thumbnail image</key>
					<string>LHCb_about.png</string>
					<key>Title</key>
					<string>LHCb</string>
				</dict>
			</array>
			<key>Title</key>
			<string>Experiments</string>
		</dict>
	</array>
</dict>
</plist>
